"happiness is a choice that requires effort," and the third is one by Groucho Marx who said, "I wouldn't want to choose to belong to any club that would have me as a member." Now, bad news: I didn't know which one of these quotes to choose and share with you. The sweet anxiety of choice. In today's times of post-industrial capitalism, choice, together with individual freedom and the idea of self-making, has been elevated to an ideal. Now, together with this, we also have a belief in endless progress. But the underside of this ideology has been an increase of anxiety, feelings of guilt, feelings of being inadequate, feeling that we are failing in our choices. Sadly, this ideology of individual choice has prevented us from thinking about social changes. It appears that this ideology was actually very efficient in pacifying us as political and social thinkers. Instead of making social critiques, we are more and more engaging in self-critique, sometimes to the point of self-destruction. Now, how come that ideology of choice is still so powerful, even among people who have not many things to choose among? How come that even people who are poor very much still identify with the idea of choice, the kind of rational idea of choice which we embrace? Now, the ideology of choice is very successful in opening for us a space to think about some imagined future. Let me give you an example.
"La felicidad es una elección que requiere esfuerzo". Y la tercera, de Groucho Marx, dice: "No elegiría pertenecer a un club que me tuviese como miembro". Ahora, las malas noticias: No sabía cuál de estas citas elegir para compartir con Uds. La dulce angustia de la elección. En el momento actual del capitalismo post-industrial, la elección, la libertad individual y la idea del hacerlo uno mismo, se elevaron al estatus de ideal. Además, tenemos la idea del progreso infinito. Pero como trasfondo de esta ideología ha habido un aumento de la angustia, del sentimiento de culpa, de ser inadecuado, de que fracasamos en nuestras elecciones. Tristemente, esta ideología de la elección individual nos ha impedido pensar los cambios sociales. Aparentemente esta ideología fue en realidad muy eficiente para pacificarnos como pensadores políticos y sociales. En vez de hacer críticas sociales, nos autocriticamos cada vez más, a veces hasta el punto de la autodestrucción. Ahora, ¿por qué esta ideología de la elección sigue siendo tan poderosa, aún en personas que no tienen muchas opciones para elegir? ¿Cómo es que incluso las personas pobres todavía se identifican tanto con la idea de elección, la idea racional de elección que adoptamos nosotros? La ideología de la elección es muy exitosa para abrirnos un espacio de pensamiento sobre futuros imaginados. Les daré un ejemplo.
My friend Manya, when she was a student at university in California, was earning money by working for a car dealer. Now, Manya, when she encountered the typical customer, would debate with him about his lifestyle, how much he wants to spend, how many children he has, what does he need the car for? They would usually come to a good conclusion what would be a perfect car. Now, before Manya's customer would go home and think things through, she would say to him, "The car that you are buying now is perfect, but in a few year's time, when your kids will be already out of the house, when you will have a little bit more money, that other car will be ideal. But what you are buying now is great." Now, the majority of Manya's customers who came back the next day bought that other car, the car they did not need, the car that cost far too much money. Now, Manya became so successful in selling cars that soon she moved on to selling airplanes. (Laughter) And knowing so much about the psychology of people prepared her well for her current job, which is that of a psychoanalyst. Now, why were Manya's customers so irrational? Manya's success was that she was able to open in their heads an image of an idealized future, an image of themselves when they are already more successful, freer, and for them, choosing that other car was as if they are coming closer to this ideal in which it was as if Manya already saw them. Now, we rarely make really totally rational choices. Choices are influenced by our unconscious, by our community. We're often choosing by guessing, what would other people think about our choice? Also we are choosing by looking at what others are choosing. We're also guessing what is socially acceptable choice. Now, because of this, we actually even after we have already chosen, like bought a car, endlessly read reviews about cars, as if we still want to convince ourselves that we made the right choice. Now, choices are anxiety-provoking. They are linked to risks, losses. They are highly unpredictable. Now, because of this, people have now more and more problems that they are not choosing anything. Not long ago, I was at a wedding reception, and I met a young, beautiful woman who immediately started telling me about her anxiety over choice. She said to me, "I needed one month to decide which dress to wear." Then she said, "For weeks I was researching which hotel to stay for this one night. And now, I need to choose a sperm donor." (Laughter) I looked at this woman in shock. "Sperm donor? What's the rush?" She said, "I'm turning 40 at the end of this year, and I've been so bad in choosing men in my life." Now choice, because it's linked to risk, is anxiety-provoking, and it was already the famous Danish philosopher Søren Kierkegaard who pointed out that anxiety is linked to the possibility of possibility. Now, we think today that we can prevent these risks. We have endless market analysis, projections of the future earnings. Even with market, which is about chance, randomness, we think we can predict rationally where it's going. Now, chance is actually becoming very traumatic. Last year, my friend Bernard Harcourt at the University of Chicago organized an event, a conference on the idea of chance. He and I were together on the panel, and just before delivering our papers — we didn't know each other's papers — we decided to take chance seriously. So we informed our audience that what they will just now hear will be a random paper, a mixture of the two papers which we didn't know what each was writing. Now, we delivered the conference in such a way. Bernard read his first paragraph, I read my first paragraph, Bernard read his second paragraph, I read my second paragraph, in this way towards the end of our papers. Now, you will be surprised that a majority of our audience did not think that what they'd just listened to was a completely random paper. They couldn't believe that speaking from the position of authority like two professors we were, we would take chance seriously. They thought we prepared the papers together and were just joking that it's random. Now, we live in times with a lot of information, big data, a lot of knowledge about the insides of our bodies. We decoded our genome. We know about our brains more than before. But surprisingly, people are more and more turning a blind eye in front of this knowledge. Ignorance and denial are on the rise. Now, in regard to the current economic crisis, we think that we will just wake up again and everything will be the same as before, and no political or social changes are needed. In regard to ecological crisis, we think nothing needs to be done just now, or others need to act before us. Or even when ecological crisis already happens, like a catastrophe in Fukushima, often we have people living in the same environment with the same amount of information, and half of them will be anxious about radiation and half of them will ignore it. Now, psychoanalysts know very well that people surprisingly don't have passion for knowledge but passion for ignorance. Now, what does that mean? Let's say when we are facing a life-threatening illness, a lot of people don't want to know that. They'd rather prefer denying the illness, which is why it's not so wise to inform them if they don't ask. Surprisingly, research shows that sometimes people who deny their illness live longer than those who are rationally choosing the best treatment. Now, this ignorance, however, is not very helpful on the level of the social. When we are ignorant about where we are heading, a lot of social damage can be caused. Now, on top of facing ignorance, we are also facing today some kind of an obviousness. Now, it was French philosopher Louis Althusser who pointed out that ideology functions in such a way that it creates a veil of obviousness. Before we do any social critique, it is necessary really to lift that veil of obviousness and to think through a little bit differently. If we go back to this ideology of individual, rational choice we often embrace, it's necessary precisely here to lift this obviousness and to think a little bit differently. Now for me, a question often is why we still embrace this idea of a self-made man on which capitalism relied from its beginning? Why do we think that we are really such masters of our lives that we can rationally make the best ideal choices, that we don't accept losses and risks? And for me, it's very shocking to see sometimes very poor people, for example, not supporting the idea of the rich being taxed more. Quite often here they still identify with a certain kind of a lottery mentality. Okay, maybe they don't think that they will make it in the future, but maybe they think, my son might become the next Bill Gates. And who would want to tax one's son? Or, a question for me is also, why would people who have no health insurance not embrace universal healthcare? Sometimes they don't embrace it, again identifying with the idea of choice, but they have nothing to choose from. Now, Margaret Thatcher famously said that there is nothing like a society. Society doesn't exist, it is only individuals and their families. Sadly, this ideology still functions very well, which is why people who are poor might feel ashamed for their poverty. We might endlessly feel guilty that we are not making the right choices, and that's why we didn't succeed. We are anxious that we are not good enough. That's why we work very hard, long hours at the workplace and equally long hours on remaking ourselves. Now, when we are anxious over choices, sometimes we easily give our power of choice away. We identify with the guru who tells us what to do, self-help therapist, or we embrace a totalitarian leader who appears to have no doubts about choices, who sort of knows. Now, often people ask me, "What did you learn by studying choice?" And there is an important message that I did learn. When thinking about choices, I stopped taking choices too seriously, personally. First, I realized a lot of choice I make is not rational. It's linked to my unconscious, my guesses of what others are choosing, or what is a socially embraced choice. I also embrace the idea that we should go beyond thinking about individual choices, that it's very important to rethink social choices, since this ideology of individual choice has pacified us. It really prevented us to think about social change. We spend so much time choosing things for ourselves and barely reflect on communal choices we can make. Now, we should not forget that choice is always linked to change. We can make individual changes, but we can make social changes. We can choose to have more wolves. We can choose to change our environment to have more bees. We can choose to have different rating agencies. We can choose to control corporations instead of allowing corporations to control us. We have a possibility to make changes. Now, I started with a quote from Samuel Johnson, who said that when we make choice in life, we shouldn't forget to live. Finally, you can see I did have a choice to choose one of the three quotes with which I wanted to start my lecture. I did have a choice, such as nations, as people, we have choices too to rethink in what kind of society we want to live in the future. Thank you. (Applause)
Mi amiga Manya, cuando estudiaba en la universidad en California ganaba dinero trabajando en una concesionaria de autos. Cuando Manya encontraba al cliente típico, hablaba con él sobre su estilo de vida, cuánto quería gastar, cuántos hijos tenía, para qué necesitaba el auto. Así llegaban a una buena conclusión de cuál sería el auto perfecto. Pero antes de que el cliente de Manya se fuese a casa y pensara en lo hablado, ella le decía: "El auto que estás comprando es perfecto ahora pero, en unos años, cuando los niños se vayan de casa, cuando tengas un poco más de dinero, aquel otro auto será ideal. Pero el que estás comprando ahora es genial". La mayoría de los clientes de Manya que volvían al día siguiente compraban ese otro auto, el que no necesitaban, el que costaba muchísimo más. Maya tuvo tanto éxito vendiendo autos que pronto pasó a vender aviones. (Risas) Saber tanto sobre la psicología humana la preparó bien para su empleo actual: es psicoanalista. Pero ¿por qué los clientes de Manya eran tan irracionales? El éxito de Manya consistía en poder despertar en sus mentes la idea de un futuro idealizado, una imagen de ellos mismos en la que ya son más exitosos, más libres, y, para ellos, elegir ese otro auto era como estar más cerca de este ideal en el que Manya ya podía verlos. Nunca elegimos de forma totalmente racional. Nuestras elecciones están influenciadas por el inconsciente, por nuestra comunidad. A menudo elegimos adivinando lo que pensarán otras personas de nuestra elección. También elegimos mirando lo que eligen otros. También adivinamos cuáles son las elecciones socialmente aceptables. Es por eso en realidad incluso después de haber elegido comprar un auto, leemos continuamente comentarios de autos, como si siguiéramos queriendo convencernos de que elegimos correctamente. Las elecciones provocan ansiedad. Están vinculadas al riesgo, a las pérdidas. Son muy impredecibles. Gracias a esto las personas tienen ahora cada vez más problemas con eso de no estar eligiendo nada. No hace mucho, estaba en una boda y conocía a una dama joven, hermosa, que de inmediato empezó a contarme de su ansiedad por la elección. Me dijo: "Necesito un mes para decidir qué vestido ponerme". Luego dijo: "Estuve investigando durante semanas en qué hotel alojarme esta noche. Y ahora tengo que elegir un donante de esperma". (Risas) Miré a esta mujer sobresaltada. "¿Donante de esperma? ¿Cuál es el apuro?" Dijo: "Cumpliré 40 a fin de año, y he elegido muy mal a los hombres en mi vida". La elección, por estar ligada al riesgo, produce ansiedad y fue el célebre filósofo danés Søren Kierkegaard que señaló que la ansiedad está vinculada a la posibilidad de la posibilidad. Hoy pensamos que esos riesgos se pueden prevenir. Tenemos interminables análisis de mercado, proyecciones de ingresos futuros. Incluso en el mercado, que depende del azar, que es aleatorio, pensamos que podemos predecir racionalmente lo que ocurre. La casualidad se está volviendo traumática. El año pasado, mi amigo Bernard Harcourt de la Universidad de Chicago organizó un evento, una conferencia sobre la idea de causalidad. Estábamos juntos en el panel, y antes de presentar nuestros artículos -- ninguno conocía el artículo del otro -- decidimos tomarnos la casualidad en serio. Así, informamos al público que lo que escucharían sería un artículo al azar, una mezcla de dos artículos y que ninguno sabía lo que había escrito el otro. De este modo dimos la conferencia. Bernard leyó su primer párrafo, yo leí mi primer párrafo, Bernard leyó su segundo párrafo, yo leí mi segundo párrafo, y así hasta el final de nuestros artículos. Les sorprenderá saber que la mayoría de nuestro público no creyó que estaban escuchando un artículo totalmente aleatorio. No podían creer que viniendo de la posición de autoridad que tenemos como profesores, tomaríamos la casualidad seriamente. Pensaron que preparamos los artículos juntos y que simplemente estábamos bromeando con lo del azar. Vivimos en una época de mucha información, de "big data", de mucho conocimiento del interior de nuestros cuerpos. Decodificamos nuestro genoma. Conocemos sobre nuestros cerebros mucho más que antes. Pero, sorprendentemente, la gente cada vez más hace la vista gorda frente a este conocimiento. La ignorancia y la negación van en aumento. Ahora, en cuanto a la crisis económica actual, pensamos que despertaremos de nuevo y todo será igual que antes, que no necesitamos cambios políticos ni sociales. En relación a la crisis ecológica, pensamos que no es necesario hacer nada ahora, o que otros tienen que actuar antes que nosotros. Incluso cuando ocurre una crisis ecológica como la catástrofe de Fukushima, a menudo tenemos personas que viven en el mismo medioambiente con la misma cantidad de información, y la mitad de ellos estarán preocupados por la radiación y la otra mitad la ignorará. Los psicólogos saben muy bien que las personas sorprendentemente no tenemos pasión por el conocimiento sino pasión por la ignorancia. ¿Qué quiere decir eso? Digamos que cuando enfrentamos una enfermedad que pone en riesgo la vida muchas personas no quieren saberlo. En vez de eso prefieren negar la enfermedad, y por eso no es bueno informarles si no preguntan. Sorprende que la investigación muestre a veces que las personas que niegan la enfermedad viven más que las que eligen racionalmente el mejor tratamiento. Esta ignorancia, no obstante, no es muy útil a nivel social. Ignorar hacia dónde vamos puede causar mucho daño social. Por encima de la ignorancia enfrentamos también hoy cierto tipo de obviedad. El filósofo francés Louis Althusser señaló que la ideología funciona en forma tal que crea un velo de obviedad. Antes de hacer cualquier crítica social es necesario levantar el velo de la obviedad y pensar en forma un poco diferente. Si desandamos esta ideología de la elección racional individual que adoptamos a menudo, es necesario precisamente aquí levantar esta obviedad y pensar de forma un poco diferente. Para mí, la pregunta a menudo es: ¿por qué seguimos aferrados a esta idea del hombre que se hace a sí mismo, que es la base del capitalismo desde su origen? ¿Por qué pensamos que tenemos tal maestría sobre nuestras vidas que podemos, en forma racional, hacer las mejores elecciones ideales y no aceptamos pérdidas ni riesgos? Me resulta muy impactante ver a veces a personas muy pobres, por ejemplo, que no apoyan la idea de que los ricos paguen más impuestos. Muy a menudo, aquí todavía se identifican con cierto tipo de mentalidad de lotería. Quizá no piensen que les tocará a ellos en el futuro, pero quizá mi hijo podría ser el próximo Bill Gates. Y ¿quién querría cobrarle impuestos a su hijo? O la pregunta para mí es también: ¿por qué las personas que no tienen seguro médico no aceptan la asistencia sanitaria universal? A veces no la aceptan por identificación con la idea de elección, pero no tienen opciones para elegir. Margaret Thatcher dijo célebremente que no hay tal cosa llamada sociedad. La sociedad no existe, hay solo individuos y sus familias. Tristemente, esta ideología todavía funciona muy bien y por eso hay personas pobres que podrían sentir vergüenza de su pobreza. Podríamos sentirnos eternamente culpables de no elegir correctamente, y por eso es que no tenemos éxito. Nos angustia no ser lo suficientemente buenos. Por eso trabajamos tan arduamente largas jornadas laborales y de igual manera muchas horas rehaciéndonos. Cuando decidir nos angustia, a veces regalamos nuestro poder de decisión. Nos identificamos con el gurú que nos dice qué hacer, con el terapeuta de autoayuda, o aceptamos un líder totalitario que parece no tener dudas sobre la elección, que parece saber. A menudo me preguntan: "¿Qué aprendiste de estudiar la elección?" Y hay un mensaje importante que aprendí. Al pensar en las elecciones, dejé de tomármelas tan en serio, en lo personal. Primero, me di cuenta de que muchas de las elecciones que hago no son racionales. Están ligadas a mi inconsciente, a lo que otros están eligiendo, o a elecciones socialmente aceptadas. También adopto la idea de que deberíamos trascender la idea de elección individual, que es muy importante para repensar las elecciones sociales, dado que esta ideología de la elección individual nos ha pacificado. En realidad nos impide pensar el cambio social. Pasamos mucho tiempo eligiendo cosas para nosotros mismos y apenas nos detenemos en las elecciones en común que podemos hacer. No deberíamos olvidar que la elección siempre está ligada al cambio. Podemos hacer elecciones individuales, pero podemos hacer cambios sociales. Podemos elegir tener más lobos. Podemos elegir cambiar nuestro ambiente para tener más abejas. Podemos elegir tener diferentes agencias de calificación. Podemos elegir controlar a las corporaciones en vez de permitirles que nos controlen. Tenemos una posibilidad de hacer cambios. Empecé con una cita de Samuel Johnson, que dijo que cuando elijas en la vida no te olvides de vivir. Para terminar, pueden ver que podía elegir una de tres citas para empezar mi conferencia. Tuve una elección, como naciones, como personas, también tenemos elecciones para repensar en qué tipo de sociedad queremos vivir en el futuro. Gracias. (Aplausos)